<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
  <title>twrl</title>
  <link href="http://twrl.github.com"/>
  <link type="application/atom+xml" rel="self" href="http://twrl.github.com/atom.xml"/>
  <updated>2013-01-30T14:34:09+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://twrl.github.com</id>
  <author>
    <name>Tom Robbins</name>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <id>http://twrl.github.com/2013/01/eyes-teeth-and-angry-postcards/</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://twrl.github.com/2013/01/eyes-teeth-and-angry-postcards/"/>
    <title>Eyes, Teeth, and Angry Postcards</title>
    <published>2013-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Tom Robbins</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Less than a year ago, I published an &lt;a href=&quot;/2012/03/open-letter-to-britains-catholics/&quot;&gt;open letter&lt;/a&gt;
in response to certain of the Roman Catholic Church&amp;rsquo;s statements in the 
earliest days of the current same-sex marriage proposals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been a very busy ten months since. I don&amp;rsquo;t think a week has gone by when I
haven&amp;rsquo;t read some misleading and outdated idea, or even outright fabrication, by
one group or another on how same-sex marriage will ruin society and why 
same-sex couples don&amp;rsquo;t deserve to be able to marry. The level of sheer 
unadulterated hatred that has been sloshing around the place has been trumped 
only by the depth of ignorance displayed by certain public figures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around the same time as that letter, I also said I was becoming fed up with the
debate. Well, I wasn&amp;rsquo;t. I&amp;rsquo;ve talked until my voice is hoarse, I&amp;rsquo;ve written until
my fingers ached, I&amp;rsquo;ve read and engaged and done my level best to display the
patience and tolerance the other side frequently won&amp;rsquo;t stoop to show me. And now
I&amp;rsquo;m tired. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, the opposing lobby have won a sort of phyrric victory when it comes to
me, and many other people I know who share my mixture of ideological liberalism
and cynical pragmatism: they&amp;rsquo;ve managed to shake my belief in the univerasality
of rights. Not uproot it, my principles remain unchanged, but how I interpret
and apply those principles has been getting some serious re-evaluation of late.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To summarise very briefly my ethical position, I believe that all people have a
right to continuity of life and integrity of self - by which I mean both that 
the individual should be protected against mental and physical harm, and that 
ones economic and social presence should not be unduly restrained or interfered
with either. I also believe that denying somebody some right is one manner of
doing them harm, and is therefore only justifiable if it prevents more harm than
it causes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this basis I have spent the last ten months arguing that same-sex couple must
be given the right to marry, because it is harmful to those couples who want or
need to do so that they can&amp;rsquo;t and there is no reason to deny it to them; and 
simultaniously that no religious group should be forced or forbidden to conduct
such ceremonies, because denying them control of their own rites does harm to
them for insufficient reason too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve argued this in the full knowledge that I&amp;rsquo;m at least in part arguing for the
very same people who so viciously oppose me. But my supplies of civility have 
now been exhausted. So I wasn&amp;rsquo;t best pleased to discover that on Sunday 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pinknews.co.uk/2013/01/28/uk-catholics-hand-out-1-million-anti-gay-marriage-postcards/&quot;&gt;a million postcards had been handed out in mass&lt;/a&gt;
as part of a last-ditch effort against the bill, nor that the Church of England
is claiming that &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pinknews.co.uk/2013/01/28/church-of-england-the-government-has-no-mandate-for-its-same-sex-marriage-bill/&quot;&gt;the government has no mandate&lt;/a&gt;, 
nor was I glad to see a number of other increasingly desperate signs from the 
anti-equality lobby. But if all they had been were the signs of an argument
near-lost I would have rolled my eyes and carried on. They&amp;rsquo;re not, this is a 
surge of energy, but relatively innocuous in terms of tactics. A few months ago
a couple of newlyweds delivered an anti-marriage equality petition to Downing
Street dressed in their wedding gear, which was a particularly vicious snub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://services.parliament.uk/bills/2012-13/marriagesamesexcouplesbill.html&quot;&gt;Marriage (Same-sex Couples) Bill&lt;/a&gt;
had it&amp;rsquo;s first reading in the House of Commons. Having cynically predicted that 
it would take a lot longer to get to this stage in order for the government to
extract the maximum amount of capital from the issue, I&amp;rsquo;ve seldom been more
happy to be wrong. The second reading is scheduled for the 5th of February. It&amp;rsquo;s
expected to pass the Commons easily enough, but the battle in the Lords will be
long and bloody and could go either way. The argument is not over yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By no means all, but most of this vitriol originates from religious groups. I
can no longer consider them irritating quirks, I find myself increasingly
seeing them as a direct and continuing cause of systematic harm. The level of 
restraint we apply no longer seems to provide the right balance between their
freedoms and everybody else&amp;rsquo;s wellbeing. Should not the additional protections
we afford religious groups be balanced by their absolute neturality on secular
matters? Is maintaining an established church still in the national interest?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These issues are not new, but for me at least they have now become pressing. The
role that organised religion plays in our society has become so divorced from
offering any good to the public, that all we see is a bunch of particularly
ineffective politicians in period costume. I&amp;rsquo;m on the fence about the continued
merit of Parliament, I certainly can&amp;rsquo;t tolerate people telling us all how to 
live whose authority might as well come from Paddington Bear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So once this present argument is over, secularism is where I must turn my mind.
It&amp;rsquo;s past time to disestablish the Church of England, it&amp;rsquo;s certainly past time
to enforce charity law on those groups that benefit from it. It&amp;rsquo;s past time we
enforced the libel laws, for that matter. Rather than simmering away in the 
background, the role of religion is something that society needs to consider 
more fully. And I for one can no longer see any merit in it.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://twrl.github.com/2013/01/the-passage-of-time/</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://twrl.github.com/2013/01/the-passage-of-time/"/>
    <title>The Passage of Time</title>
    <published>2013-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2013-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Tom Robbins</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Well, it&amp;rsquo;s been a rather fraught few months, to put it mildly. Lots has happened
in the world - not to mention in my life - and although I&amp;rsquo;ve accumulated a lot
of skeletons of posts since October, I&amp;rsquo;ve published none.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, here&amp;rsquo;s the highlights&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;october&quot;&gt;October&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Term started again in October, and we had the now-notorious 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.huffingtonpost.co.uk/2012/10/04/reading-university-atheist-society-thrown-out-blasphemous-mohammed-pineapple_n_1939317.html&quot;&gt;Pineapple Incident&lt;/a&gt;. 
I&amp;rsquo;m in the Reading University Atheist society, although I wasn&amp;rsquo;t there for this 
and wasn&amp;rsquo;t directly involved. looking at some of the discussion afterwards 
however, I think two things became pretty clear: most of RAHS really did not
(and still don&amp;rsquo;t) understand what the original problem was, myself included; and
RUSU couldn&amp;rsquo;t have handled the incident or it&amp;rsquo;s aftermath worse if they&amp;rsquo;d tried,
rather than deal with it constructively and move on they&amp;rsquo;ve opened this huge can
of proverbial worms about democracy, transparency, and free expression. I may 
yet recycle the stuff I&amp;rsquo;d started writing about the balance between prohibiting 
hate speech (which is harmful), and permitting critical speech (which may 
sometimes be offensive, but is not harmful).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Otherwise, in terms of things to talk about, October was a pretty quiet month. 
there was the usual start-of-the-academic-year celebrating, and and whole great 
swathes of new mathematics to learn, but nothing terribly noteworthy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;november&quot;&gt;November&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;November started abysmally, with me and the boyfriend parting company. After a 
few days of staying in my room, listening to excessively loud music and living 
on vodka and granola bars I did start to pull myself together and carry on with
life. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only to fall ill a couple of weeks later. A trip to the hospital, a dozen trips
to the GP, and and more vacutainers of blood than I can possibly count later, 
the solution turns out to be to wait it out (with the help of a lot of tramadol)
and then do all sorts of lifestyle improving stuff to stop it happening again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, between wallowing in self-pity and wallowing in a pain-and-opiate mediated 
stupor, I missed most of November.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;december&quot;&gt;December&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;December started as November had finished: blurrily. I did manage to get on to
campus - attend a few lectures, meetings, and so on - but too often putting in a
few hours would leave me crippled for the following few days. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mid-month, we had the government&amp;rsquo;s latest interation of it&amp;rsquo;s proposals for 
same-sex marriage. The Church of England had a hissy fit because they were 
outwitted on the issue, and the Pope decided to use World Peace Day to 
(re-)declare war.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Term ended, I went to stay with my parents over the vacation, and subsequently
endured the eternal chaotic grind of my family at Christmas. We&amp;rsquo;re all still 
speaking, so it can&amp;rsquo;t be that bad really.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://twrl.github.com/2012/09/the-fsf-have-my-goat/</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://twrl.github.com/2012/09/the-fsf-have-my-goat/"/>
    <title>The FSF have my goat!</title>
    <published>2012-09-26T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-09-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Tom Robbins</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve never made a secret of my mixed feelings about the FSF and what they do. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For anyone who isn&amp;rsquo;t aware, the UEFI forum have devised a standard called
Secure Boot. Secure Boot requires the firmware to cryptographically verify
operating system images at load time, using public keys stored in NVRAM. The
standard doesn&amp;rsquo;t require it explicitly, but in practice this means using the 
secure keystore and trusted boot path functions of a Trusted Platform Module.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Microsoft have stated that for hardware manufacturers to recieve Windows 8 logo
certification they must meet certain requirements regarding Secure Boot. Amongst
other things Secure Boot must be fully implemented the user must be able to 
disable Secure Boot on x86 and x86-64 based systems. Meaning that as well as the
UEFI mandated software API for disabling and overriding the behaviour of Secure
Boot, Microsoft have mandated that there must be a user interface. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The computer, and the vast majority of the world&amp;rsquo;s computers are sold 
preinstalled with Microsoft Windows, must be able to verify that the core of the
operating system is untampered with at boot-time. And the user must be able to
disable this function. These requirements seem thoroughly reasonable, and 
address the spectre of UEFI and Hypervisor malwares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why does the front page of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fsf.org&quot;&gt;FSF website&lt;/a&gt; look like
this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;width: 100%&quot; src=&quot;/attachments/2012-09-26-fsf.org-screenshot.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only explanation I can think of is that the FSF are so invested in the idea
of every development being a Microsoft led conspiracy against freedom that they
can&amp;rsquo;t not spin things like this any more. In fact, anyone who does comply with
Microsofts certification requirements has already met the demands stated in the
FSF petition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are plenty of very legitimate grievances against Microsoft, but this not 
one of them. For the time being, at least, Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s policy seems quite 
reasonable and quite responsible. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Microsoft has the clout to get it&amp;rsquo;s public keys included in practially every 
firmware, and the corporate world will have no compunction about getting their
certificates signed by Microsoft. Red Hat have announced their intention to do
just that for the Fedora Linux distribution. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But never in a million years will the FSF let Microsoft sign their certificates,
for ideological reasons. They have already condemned Red Hat for doing so.
The FSF&amp;rsquo;s intentions may be pure, but they&amp;rsquo;re politically very divisive. If the
whole Open Source and Free Software communities were to unite behind the FSF, 
then their keys could well be in every firmware just like Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s. But that
will never happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s time to consider the role of the FSF, and whether they now do more harm 
than good for the movement that they once nurtured.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://twrl.github.com/2012/09/processor-of-my-dreams/</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://twrl.github.com/2012/09/processor-of-my-dreams/"/>
    <title>The Processor of my Dreams</title>
    <published>2012-09-21T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-09-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Tom Robbins</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My recent forays into Operating System Development have made me more aware of 
the pros and cons of the x86 processor. It&amp;rsquo;s not all bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is impressive that software written for the 8086, which was released 35 years
ago, will still run without modification on the latest Intel i7 or AMD A-series.
But it&amp;rsquo;s also a burden, because as anyone who has ever tried to manipulate the
Global Descriptor Table will tell you, holding on to back-compatibility has
led to some hideously fragmented data structures and seemingly nonsense 
behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, this set me to thinking about what features I would like in a processor.
In terms of what I&amp;rsquo;d like to see in a future iteration of the x86, we have:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;128-bit General Purpose registers. Bonus points if it can be initialized
with random data (for UUID generation), and if you can lock the value of the
high n-bits (for working with IPv6 addresses).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hardware synchronisation primitives. It would be simple to add a circuit
connected to all (logical) cores which allows you to add, test, and remove
an integer from a list of active locks. In multi-chip setups you&amp;rsquo;d need some
sort of memory coherence to keep each chip in sync, but we&amp;rsquo;d be talking 
of quite small amounts of data on fast buses and independent of the main
load-store unit.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Updated configuration and mode selection mechanism. I understand why the x86
has fixed data structures and an array of registers to set it&amp;rsquo;s operating
mode and configuration, but it&amp;rsquo;s a nightmare. There are three million steps
to do anything, most processor features are controlled in fundamentally
different ways, and the BIOS/EFI/Bootloader/etc. may or may not have already
set or unset various things - including some which can&amp;rsquo;t easily be tested
for. By all means keep these things for legacy support. But why not
implement a new, simple, single configuration meachanism. I want to say 
&amp;ldquo;load a 24-byte configuration packet from this address&amp;rdquo; and have the CPU
execute my instructions. You can have variable length packets, make it
arbitrarily extensible. You can even include a query mechanism in the 
protocol and make it bidirectional. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now if I were designing a new CPU, there&amp;rsquo;s a few things I&amp;rsquo;d add to this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Seperate call and data stacks. Keeping track of the stack frame is fiddly,
and for low level programming unwinding exceptions is impractical, when you
have a single stack.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Structure mutation area. Why not have a 1024-bit register, into which you 
can load a large data structure? Make it size-aligned subaddressable (so 128 
bytes, or 64 words, or 32 dwords, or 16 qwords, etc). Then you can do 
mutations of that data structure, which because it&amp;rsquo;s a CPU register will be 
very fast and cheap, and flush it back out to main memory once you&amp;rsquo;re done.
For 128 bytes natural aligned it so happens there&amp;rsquo;s a very efficient coding
of all possible size/offset combinations into 1 byte too :)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s almost certainly more things I could add to this. Mechanisms to enforce
bounds on data structures, to resolve arbitrary identifiers to pointers, and
to fire arbitrary events (interrupts and exceptions being a hardware-defined
subset of &amp;lsquo;event&amp;rsquo;) all spring to mind. Slightly more outlandish, but the ability
to emulate CAM in main memory might be fun (and could underpin several of the
above).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Un)fortunately I know very little about CPU microarchitecture, and Verilog 
makes my head hurt, so Intel and AMD are safe from competetion. For now&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://twrl.github.com/2012/09/operating-system-development/</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://twrl.github.com/2012/09/operating-system-development/"/>
    <title>Operating System Development</title>
    <published>2012-09-12T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-09-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Tom Robbins</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;To amuse myself while I wait for the new term to start in a few weeks time, I&amp;rsquo;ve
turned to a very old friend - osdev.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was a teenager I dabbled in Operatng Systems quite a lot. I had some 
great vision of how a new operating system should be, but of course I lacked
both the patience and the knowledge to actually bring it about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m somewhat older and wiser now, so maybe I&amp;rsquo;ll get a little further than 
printing &amp;ldquo;hello world&amp;rdquo;. At the moment, I&amp;rsquo;m just trying out some ideas in a very
simple kernel or two, but I think I&amp;rsquo;ll sketch out a proper design and go for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, here&amp;rsquo;s a few general osdev resources for anyone interested:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://wiki.osdev.org&quot;&gt;osdev.org wiki&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.osdever.net&quot;&gt;Bona Fide OS Developer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nondot.org/sabre/os/articles&quot;&gt;The Operating System Resource Centre&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.acm.uiuc.edu/sigops/roll_your_own/&quot;&gt;How to Write an Operating System&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.brokenthorn.com/Resources/OSDevIndex.html&quot;&gt;BrokenThorn OS Development&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lmgtfy.com/?q=os+development&quot;&gt;and there are many more out there&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://twrl.github.com/2012/08/multiple-representations/</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://twrl.github.com/2012/08/multiple-representations/"/>
    <title>Multiple Representations</title>
    <published>2012-08-31T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-08-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Tom Robbins</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Well, I now have an arrangement which provides multiple views of the pages of 
this website. Believe me, that was difficult to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d investigated quite a few different Jekyll plugins, and when I couldn&amp;rsquo;t find
one to do what I wanted I investigated quite a few different approaches to
writing Jekyll plugins. But then I realised, I can do what I need far more
simply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been thinking about the relationship between resources and their
representations. I wrote recently about the difference an &lt;code&gt;/index.html&lt;/code&gt; makes.
So I just wrote another theme, because I&amp;rsquo;m using a fork of &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/josegonzalez/cimino&quot;&gt;Cimino&lt;/a&gt;
and themes are pretty easy, and I merge
files in each view of the site with the command&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;rename s/index/mobile/ `find _site -name *.html`
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;before merging the two file trees together. It&amp;rsquo;s perhaps not the most elegant 
solution, but it works surprisingly well.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://twrl.github.com/2012/08/httprange-14-and-the-dark-resource/</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://twrl.github.com/2012/08/httprange-14-and-the-dark-resource/"/>
    <title>httpRange-14 and the Dark Resource</title>
    <published>2012-08-29T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-08-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Tom Robbins</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In web parlance, a resource is any identifiable thing. A resource need not have a digital representation, and the representation of a resource may also be a distinct resource in it&amp;rsquo;s own right. There is a whole gamut of issues about resources, possibly the best known is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2001/tag/issues.html#httpRange-14&quot;&gt;httpRange-14&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of these questions only become important when you start getting involved with Semantic Web technology. For example, is this properly described as a web page or as a blog post?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hold to the convention that &lt;code&gt;http://twrl.github.com/2012/08/httprange-14-and-the-dark-resource/&lt;/code&gt; is distinct from &lt;code&gt;http://twrl.github.com/2012/08/httprange-14-and-the-dark-resource/index.html&lt;/code&gt;. They&amp;rsquo;re related, very much so, but distinct. In particular&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;@base &amp;lt;http://twrl.github.com/&amp;gt;
@prefix schema: &amp;lt;http://schema.org/&amp;gt;
@prefix dc: &amp;lt;http://purl.org/dc/terms/&amp;gt;

&amp;lt;/2012/08/httprange-14-and-the-dark-resource&amp;gt; a schema:BlogPost;
	dc:hasFormat &amp;lt;/2012/08/httprange-14-and-the-dark-resource/index.html&amp;gt;.

&amp;lt;/2012/08/httprange-14-and-the-dark-resource/index.html&amp;gt; a schema:WebPage.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From this point of view, there are a lot of &amp;ldquo;missing&amp;rdquo; resources out there - ones which are not described. Taking the view that the abstract resource and it&amp;rsquo;s representation are distinct, people mostly seem to describe only one of the two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But why does this matter, you may say. Well, what a person wants to access is the abstract, logical resource. But what they need is it&amp;rsquo;s representation, and given the variety of media through which we can access the web - smartphones, tablets, TVs, etc - they need the right representation. Having the correct semantics makes it possible to identify the best of many possible representations, as well as allowing better indexes.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://twrl.github.com/2012/08/static-site-generators/</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://twrl.github.com/2012/08/static-site-generators/"/>
    <title>Static Site Generators</title>
    <published>2012-08-26T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-08-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Tom Robbins</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m using Jekyll to maintain this site. I first started doing so because it was convenient
to serve from Github pages, but now I run Jekyll locally in order to support customisation
and plugins which I can&amp;rsquo;t have if I run it on Github.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll itself is fine. There are a few things which niggle at me, but that would be true
for anything. The joy of using open source software is that you can modify and adapt your
way around anything that you don&amp;rsquo;t like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an argument that &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jeremyscheff.com/2011/08/jekyll-and-other-static-site-generators-are-currently-harmful-to-the-free-open-source-software-movement/&quot;&gt;static site generators are harmful&lt;/a&gt; to FOSS. The 
reasoning is that we expect a certain level of dynamic and interactive content - 
commenting, sharing, and so forth - and by using a static generator to maintain a website 
we&amp;rsquo;re also tying ourselves in to third parties and their proprietary infrastructures. For
example, if you scroll down this page, you&amp;rsquo;ll see a Disqus comments box at the bottom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t particularly care about that though. I don&amp;rsquo;t share &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/who-does-that-server-really-serve.html&quot;&gt;RMS&amp;rsquo; aversion to SaaS&lt;/a&gt;. But I do care about the functionality that I can build on top of the
platform that I&amp;rsquo;m using.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll limits me somewhat because it&amp;rsquo;s written in Ruby, which I don&amp;rsquo;t know very well 
(having only started learning it recently) and don&amp;rsquo;t especially like (no curly brackets).
I&amp;rsquo;m sure I&amp;rsquo;ll get used to it, but for the time being I can&amp;rsquo;t easily knock something
together and play with it. I&amp;rsquo;m still at the stage where making quite simple tweaks is a
fairly involved process with lots of to-ing and fro-ing with language guides and API docs.
I may or may not stick with Jekyll in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I&amp;rsquo;ve definitely seen the light when it comes to static site generators. Static content
is easy to host and easy to serve. Yes, I would like to integrate my own dynamic elements
too, but that&amp;rsquo;s a fair way down my list of priorities. What I want is to be able to take 
my data, and churn out a website. And although there&amp;rsquo;s functionality which I can&amp;rsquo;t
implement with Jekyll, that&amp;rsquo;s as much down to my limitations as Jekyll&amp;rsquo;s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As client side development has become more and more powerful, the need for server-side
dynamics has diminished. We&amp;rsquo;ve reached a point where only a very small number of services
have to be on a server, and most of those are some kind of database endpoint or security
system. I don&amp;rsquo;t actually need PHP or Node or ASP.Net to generate my pages if I want to host
my own comments - I can do the presentation work on the client - I just need a RESTful 
JSON store with some basic anti-spamming logic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somewhat circuitously, this brings me back to data portability and distributed social
networking. If I can have my RESTful data buckets, I can take responsibility for exposing
their content (or not). I can set aside a bucket or two for the dynamic elements of my
website. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s what Jekyll has shown me - I don&amp;rsquo;t need to be dynamic on the server.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://twrl.github.com/2012/08/XBMC/</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://twrl.github.com/2012/08/XBMC/"/>
    <title>Media Centre</title>
    <published>2012-08-14T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-08-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Tom Robbins</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;I had an entertaining time at the weekend setting up &lt;a href=&quot;http://xbmc.org&quot;&gt;XBMC&lt;/a&gt; on my laptop.
It runs well enough on Ubuntu, and compiling the latest source was pretty easy (the 
instructions are pretty good).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran into a few problems. My CPU usage is a little on the high side. My laptop 
being an ageing MacBook, so it&amp;rsquo;s prone to run hot, and unnecessary CPU usage = unnecessary 
fan noise. Getting Suspend and Wake-on-Lan to work reliably was also tricky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cpu-usage&quot;&gt;CPU Usage&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing to do is enable 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://wiki.xbmc.org/index.php?title=Dirty_regions&quot;&gt;Dirty Regions&lt;/a&gt;. Trial and error will 
tell you which of the available algorithms gives you the best results on you hardware. For
my Macbook (which has an Intel GMA 950 graphics chipset) I found mode 2 worked best, but
YMMV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also recommend disabling RSS feeds on the home screen, and trying a few different skins.
Aeon skins tend to be heavy CPU eaters, although I found Aeon Nox to be better than the
default Confluence skin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;suspend-and-wol&quot;&gt;Suspend and WoL&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was having an issue with suspend, whether I triggered it from within XBMC or from the 
Unity panel: the computer would enter suspend and then immediately wake itself. 
It never did this if I just closed the lid and left it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution was to tweak a setting in grub.cfg. Find the line which sets &lt;code&gt;GRUB_CMDLINE_LINUX_DEFAULT&lt;/code&gt;
and add &lt;code&gt;usbcore.autosuspend=-1&lt;/code&gt; to it. So it might read&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;GRUB_CMDLINE_LINUX_DEFAULT=&quot;quiet splash usbcore.autosuspend=-1&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;or something similar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To enable Wake-on-LAN you need to first enable it in the BIOS, if applicable. I didn&amp;rsquo;t have
to - by some quirk of Apple&amp;rsquo;s EFI implementation it seems to be supported anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I installed ethtool, and enabled WoL on the NIC using the command&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo ethtool -s et0 wol g
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is all documented on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://help.ubuntu.com/community/WakeOnLan&quot;&gt;Ubuntu Community Docs&lt;/a&gt;.
The only trouble is, you have to do this every time the network interface comes up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, there are all sorts of issues around integration of ethtool and NetworkManager, which
Ubuntu uses by default. I found that the best thing to do was to create a script in 
&lt;code&gt;/etc/NetworkManager/dispatcher.d&lt;/code&gt; to trigger ethtool. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dispatcher.d directory contains scripts which are executed every time an interface 
changes state in NetworkManager. I simply created a file called &lt;code&gt;99wol&lt;/code&gt; and put this in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;CodeRay&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#n1&quot; name=&quot;n1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;directive&quot;&gt;#!/bin/sh&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#n2&quot; name=&quot;n2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#n3&quot; name=&quot;n3&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;instance-variable&quot;&gt;IF&lt;/span&gt;=&lt;span class=&quot;predefined-constant&quot;&gt;$1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#n4&quot; name=&quot;n4&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;instance-variable&quot;&gt;STATUS&lt;/span&gt;=&lt;span class=&quot;predefined-constant&quot;&gt;$2&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#n5&quot; name=&quot;n5&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#n6&quot; name=&quot;n6&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;reserved&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;reserved&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;delimiter&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;instance-variable&quot;&gt;$IF&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;delimiter&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; = &lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;delimiter&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;eth0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;delimiter&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;reserved&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &amp;amp;&amp;amp; &lt;span class=&quot;reserved&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;delimiter&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;instance-variable&quot;&gt;$STATUS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;delimiter&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; = &lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;delimiter&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;up&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;delimiter&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;reserved&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;delimiter&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;reserved&quot;&gt;then&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#n7&quot; name=&quot;n7&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#n8&quot; name=&quot;n8&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;    ethtool -s eth0 wol g
&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#n9&quot; name=&quot;n9&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#n10&quot; name=&quot;n10&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;reserved&quot;&gt;fi&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is almost certainly some more sophisticated logic one could employ, but it does the
job I need.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://twrl.github.com/2012/08/microdata-vs-rdfa/</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://twrl.github.com/2012/08/microdata-vs-rdfa/"/>
    <title>Microdata vs RDFa</title>
    <published>2012-08-13T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-08-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Tom Robbins</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;To my shame, I&amp;rsquo;ve largely ignored the development of microdata until very recently. I&amp;rsquo;ve 
been aware of it going on in the background, but I&amp;rsquo;ve been far more concerned with RDFa
and JSON-LD when it comes to semantics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google told me that they were favouring microdata for semantic markup, so I looked
into it. At first, I was rather taken by it&amp;rsquo;s simplicity. There is much less mucking about
with CURIEs and namespaces than in RDFa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the novelty wore off however, I started to see the cracks. Microdata is designed very
much to be accessible to designers. RDFa is a more complicated embedding of RDF into HTML,
which means it can encode more complex parts of the graph more succinctly. It also 
lacks many of the ambiguities that microdata can introduce around dereferencing terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which is not to say that microdata is without it&amp;rsquo;s merits - far from it. Microdata is
a simpler embedding of RDF into HTML, which means it can encode simpler parts of the RDF
graph more succinctly than RDFa can. It&amp;rsquo;s more human-writable, and somewhat simpler to 
parse. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both are equally as expressive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new RDFa 1.1 recommendation has absorbed a lot of lessons both from it&amp;rsquo;s predecessor,
and from the development of microdata. RDFa began life as one module in the XHTML2 
development effort, and now stands apart from the development of HTML and XHTML as a 
separate-but-related entity. So there is plenty of room to revise and update RDFa as
technologies and practices change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to stick with RDFa. The reason is simple - I don&amp;rsquo;t want to simply annotate a
few properties here and there, I want to converge semantic, structural and presentational
data. RDFa, which more closely reflects the underlying RDF graph, meshes more easily for
me with other ways of expressing RDF - like RDF/XML and JSON-LD.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://twrl.github.com/2012/08/copyright/</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://twrl.github.com/2012/08/copyright/"/>
    <title>Copyright</title>
    <published>2012-08-05T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-08-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Tom Robbins</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For the last several months I&amp;rsquo;ve been trying to move away from iTunes as my media library.
Alas, this is a pipe dream, because I have made the mistake in the past of buying movies 
and TV shows through the iTunes store.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several years ago, Apple abandoned their ironically named FairPlay DRM software for music
and music videos, however it it still used for movies and TV shows bought through the 
iTunes store. This presents a quandary, because from Apple&amp;rsquo;s point of view they have sold 
me a copyright license to this content, and by doing so through the iTunes store have 
taken steps to ensure I can benefit from this license. However, from my point of view I 
have been sold a good, or at a pinch a service, which has not been consistently rendered -
I am unable to consume media which I have legitimately paid for in the manner that I would
wish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I&amp;rsquo;m sure that somewhere in the terms of use of the iTunes store that I clicked
through without reading, I agreed to use iTunes in perpetuity for all my media viewing 
needs, and thus it&amp;rsquo;s my own fault. There is probably some clever legalese in there which
gets around this kind of vendor lock-in being illegal in most jurisdictions of the world
too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact is that Apple have taken my money and failed to provide in exchange the media for
which it was given in a format acceptable to me. I&amp;rsquo;m sure no actual liability would attach
to Apple for this; legally they should be able to afford to cover their own backsides 
adequately, and anyway they are beholden to the studios and others who license this 
content to them for distribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The immediate lesson for people is: &lt;strong&gt;DO NOT BUY STUFF FROM THE iTunes STORE&lt;/strong&gt;, but I&amp;rsquo;m
sure that&amp;rsquo;s obvious. It does however point to a whole slew of issues to do with the
inadequacies of how we deal with digital content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trouble is that when we purchase some digital content, whether it&amp;rsquo;s music or a video 
or a game or anything else, it exists in a sort of limbo. From the point of view of the 
vendor, it&amp;rsquo;s inevitably seen as a copyright license to be defended. From the point of 
view of the consumer, it&amp;rsquo;s seen as a good to be used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I were a corporation, I could license come intellectual property under contract and be 
held to that contract. However, in the normal course of things I would not expect hourly 
audits, monitoring of my day to day activities, cryptographic measures to prevent me 
viewing the licensed property, or punitive enforcement measures. That we do expect these 
things suggests that we are far outside the scope of normal copyright license agreements. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s stop pretending that digital goods are the same as copyright licenses, and equally
let&amp;rsquo;s not pretend that they&amp;rsquo;re the same as something you might pick off a shelf. We have
to admit that digital artefacts are a unique species of thing, and that attempts to 
control them under the old systems are failing. As it stands, there is a strengthening
argument for the total abolition of copyright, and that argument is predicated on the 
excesses of copyright law used to protect digital property. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are four major forms of intellectual property rights: copyright, patents, trade
marks, and trade secrets. Each of these, in principle, serves a purpose as sound now as
when Queen Anne enacted the very first copyright statute 300 years ago. When somebody
creates something of worth, in exchange for sharing it with society they gain a temporary
monopoly on making any profit from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in exchange for buying something, a consumer should gain the right to enjoy it at
their leisure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, one can argue that copyrights on the order of a century or more are not what anyone
originally had in mind. Perhaps more importantly, one can argue that nobody intended for 
it to become illegal to know &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Illegal_prime&quot;&gt;certain integers&lt;/a&gt;.
But it&amp;rsquo;s difficult to believe that licensees were supposed to be limited in their
enjoyment of the content that they license. Gutenberg could have made a fortune if he 
had been able to charge extra for the right to read his bibles on Tuesday, or with brown
eyes instead of blue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Equally, ownership of a good does not limit what you do with it because you cannot 
duplicate it at negligible cost like you can with computer data. I can&amp;rsquo;t press a button 
and turn one hammer into two, and my friends can&amp;rsquo;t take a look at my hammer and 
automatically gain one of their own. There is a reason why the sale of goods is an 
inadequate model for the sale of digital artefacts, just as copyright licensing is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For digital goods copyright laws are not equitable to consumers, and sale of goods laws
are not equitable to vendors. But for too long now copyright vendors have been benefiting
from the excesses that the prevailing copyright model allows them, and it&amp;rsquo;s beginning to
crumble. Unless a new model can be found for digital content, then we can expect copyright
to become hateful and worthless in spite of it&amp;rsquo;s merits.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://twrl.github.com/2012/07/is-the-public-key-infrastructure-collapsing/</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://twrl.github.com/2012/07/is-the-public-key-infrastructure-collapsing/"/>
    <title>Is the Public Key Infrastructure Collapsing?</title>
    <published>2012-07-17T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-17T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Tom Robbins</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Back in February, TrustWave hit the news with tales of selling intermediate CA certificates
for use in Man-in-the-Middle traffic interception. TrustWave were redeemed somewhat by
having already revoked the offending certificate before voluntarily disclosing what they
had done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For most users, security hinges on SSL/TLS to provide an encrypted connection, and X.509
PKI to provide certificates all the way up to a small number of trusted roots. A large
number will be aware of the terms SSL and certificate from their web browser, but may
not understand what they mean or how they work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The TrustWave incident has been a reminder of just how much trust we place in the root CAs.
In theory we have assurances in the form of CSPs and independent audits against those
policies. But it seems that WebTrust, who audit for TrustWave, were not aware of the 
offending intermediate CA certificate. TrustWave have implied strongly that they are not
the only ones to have sold intermediate certificates either. It&amp;rsquo;s difficult to have faith
in the public key infrastructure under such circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But add to that, we have the looming 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://wiki.openrightsgroup.org/wiki/Communications_Data_Bill&quot;&gt;Communications Data Bill&lt;/a&gt;
which, amongst other unsavoury things, can be used to mandate Man-in-the-Middle attacks on
TLS sessions - and presumably similar interception of VPN, Tor and other encrypted traffic.
This brings the whole concept of centralised hierarchical trust, which underlies PKI, into 
question. We have no assurance that the entities at the top of the hierarchy are 
trustworthy - in fact, we have good reason to suspect that they may not be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The alternative model to PKI is the Web of Trust. This is best known for it&amp;rsquo;s use in PGP.
The main problem with the web of trust is accumulating sufficient endorsement for one&amp;rsquo;s 
certificate to be trusted everywhere. This makes it very difficult to use web of trust for
infrastructure applications. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1992, when Phil Zimmermann first put forward the web of trust as the central concept for
PGP&amp;rsquo;s key management, we didn&amp;rsquo;t have social networks like we do now. The concept of a 
Friend-to-Friend network was very much a niche one. Average Joe user would not be carrying
around the necessary data, and would not know or have remote access to it, to create the
necessary links. Now however, in the day of home servers, smartphones, and web interfaces,
there is no reason why the web of trust should not be reinvigorated as part of the 
distributed social graph. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another advantage of this is that it moves the trust policy decision back to the user. As
it stands, the majority of Firefox users trust whomever Mozilla have decided to trust, the
majority of IE users trust whomever Microsoft have decided to trust, and so on. 
Decentralising trust will allow users to make their own decisions about trust metrics,
transitivity, and so on. This entails some user education, but user interaction has come on
a long way in recent years and the concept of implicit and explicit trust shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be too
difficult to grasp, even if the technical details are more tricky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like IPv6 migration, we will likely remain with the existing infrastructure until it 
becomes untenable. Personally, I am no longer comfortable with the centralised nature of 
it, but keeping PKI is better than giving up TLS. &lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://twrl.github.com/2012/07/the-new-setup/</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://twrl.github.com/2012/07/the-new-setup/"/>
    <title>About This New Setup</title>
    <published>2012-07-16T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Tom Robbins</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So, this new setup is more or less as I want it. I somewhat prematurely put it live on 
Github pages on Saturday, even though I&amp;rsquo;m continuing to tinker with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started off using &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllbootstrap.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll-Bootstrap&lt;/a&gt;. This was a massive
timesaver. I&amp;rsquo;ve used Liquid before, so the Jekyll learning curve was very easy for me, but 
if you haven&amp;rsquo;t then I recommend Jekyll-Bootstrap as a way of easing the transition. The 
templates and includes that Jade has in there are fairly adaptable, and you can learn 
quite a bit just from examining them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the advice in &lt;a href=&quot;http://charliepark.org/jekyll-with-plugins/&quot;&gt;Charlie Park&amp;rsquo;s blog&lt;/a&gt;
I&amp;rsquo;ve got Jekyll running locally, and I&amp;rsquo;m pushing the compiled static site onto Github.
This gives me a free hand to have plugins, non-Github-supported configuration options,
and otherwise be tampering with Jekyll. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m using &lt;a href=&quot;http://kramdown.rubyforge.org/&quot;&gt;Kramdown&lt;/a&gt; and 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://coderay.rubychan.de/&quot;&gt;Coderay&lt;/a&gt; for rendering. Getting Pygments to work reliably on 
my Mac was just too much of a headache, plus I like Kramdown&amp;rsquo;s language extensions anyway. 
At least on my Mac, I had to set Kramdown&amp;rsquo;s entity_output to symbolic, otherwise it was 
garbling apostrophes and other entities. No other problems there though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m using Jekyll&amp;rsquo;s latent semantic indexing to generate the related posts list, but I&amp;rsquo;m 
not convinced about it. I really don&amp;rsquo;t want to maintain the list manually if I can avoid 
it, so next on the agenda is to investigate other options for that. I also plan to 
refactor the templates to improve the quality of the semantics in them, and because I&amp;rsquo;ve ended 
up with a small mess of css files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My only grumble is Liquid&amp;rsquo;s inability to sort an array before iterating over it. So far 
I&amp;rsquo;ve managed to work around it, but it is a nuisance. &lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://twrl.github.com/2012/07/the-new-edition/</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://twrl.github.com/2012/07/the-new-edition/"/>
    <title>The New Edition</title>
    <published>2012-07-14T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-07-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Tom Robbins</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The long-awaited redo of this blog is at hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a brief bout of insanity brought on by spending too much time with Blogger&amp;rsquo;s excuse 
for a template system, I realised: I don&amp;rsquo;t need all that complexity. Browsing around for 
something with which to replace Blogger, and preferably not add too much to the vast
number of accounts I&amp;rsquo;m dragging around with me, I stumbled onto Jekyll. And so, here we
are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, it&amp;rsquo;s been some time since I last sunk my teeth into a new language, and learning Ruby
has been on my to-do list for a while. So not only am I using Jekyll to maintain my blog, 
I&amp;rsquo;m progressively tampering with it in an effort to learn Ruby. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;http://charliepark.org/jekyll-with-plugins/&quot;&gt;Charlie Park&lt;/a&gt; for his
amazingly useful article on how to cope with Github Pages not supporting Jekyll plugins.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://twrl.github.com/2012/06/views-dynamic-and-otherwise/</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://twrl.github.com/2012/06/views-dynamic-and-otherwise/"/>
    <title>Views, dynamic and otherwise</title>
    <published>2012-06-14T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-06-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Tom Robbins</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve changed theme on this blog. I was using Dynamic Views, and now I&amp;rsquo;m using a generic Awesome Inc. theme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love the way Dynamic Views looks. It&amp;rsquo;s very sleek, but it&amp;rsquo;s impossible to adapt. After a dozen attempts I gave up getting &lt;a href=&quot;http://alexgorbatchev.com/SyntaxHighlighter/&quot;&gt;Alex Gorbatchev&amp;rsquo;s SyntaxHighlighter&lt;/a&gt; to work with it, and a brief experiment with altering the CSS ended very badly indeed - it looked like a clown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So to solve the first of those two problems I have switched to an old-style theme temporarily, while I write my own. This is not how I&amp;rsquo;d planned on spending the rest of my day, but I suppose my CSS skills could benefit from some practice. So look out for some new shiny, coming soon to a blog near you&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://twrl.github.com/2012/06/iconiser/</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://twrl.github.com/2012/06/iconiser/"/>
    <title>Iconiser</title>
    <published>2012-06-14T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-06-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Tom Robbins</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is a useful titbit for anyone who is working with blogger templates or other things that severely limit your ability to host and serve lots of little files. I just hacked it together now to implement the new theme I&amp;rsquo;m writing for this blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m using quite a few icons in the new theme and I wanted to embed them as data: URIs. The trouble is, I&amp;rsquo;m using the same icon in several places which means duplication, and having great blocks of base64 embedded in the code is making it all unreadable. So I&amp;rsquo;ve written a tiny jQuery plugin to maintain a catalogue of named icons, and then replace the shorthand URIs that I&amp;rsquo;m using with the full one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the code:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;CodeRay&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#n1&quot; name=&quot;n1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; (&lt;span class=&quot;predefined&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;) {
&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#n2&quot; name=&quot;n2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#n3&quot; name=&quot;n3&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;predefined&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span class=&quot;function&quot;&gt;iconise&lt;/span&gt; = &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; (name, data) {
&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#n4&quot; name=&quot;n4&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;        &lt;span class=&quot;predefined&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;.iconise.data[name] = data;
&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#n5&quot; name=&quot;n5&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;    }
&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#n6&quot; name=&quot;n6&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#n7&quot; name=&quot;n7&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;predefined&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;.iconise.data = {};
&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#n8&quot; name=&quot;n8&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#n9&quot; name=&quot;n9&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;predefined&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;.fn.&lt;span class=&quot;function&quot;&gt;iconise&lt;/span&gt; = &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; () {
&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#n10&quot; name=&quot;n10&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;        &lt;span class=&quot;predefined&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;delimiter&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;img&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;delimiter&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&quot;local-variable&quot;&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;).each(&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; () {
&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#n11&quot; name=&quot;n11&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;            &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; src = &lt;span class=&quot;predefined&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span class=&quot;local-variable&quot;&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;).attr(src);
&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#n12&quot; name=&quot;n12&quot;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;            &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; (src.indexOf(&lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;delimiter&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;iconise:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;delimiter&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;) == &lt;span class=&quot;integer&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;) {
&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#n13&quot; name=&quot;n13&quot;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;                &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; icon = src.substring(&lt;span class=&quot;integer&quot;&gt;8&lt;/span&gt;);
&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#n14&quot; name=&quot;n14&quot;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;                &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; (&lt;span class=&quot;predefined&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;.iconise.data[icon] !== &lt;span class=&quot;predefined-constant&quot;&gt;undefined&lt;/span&gt;) {
&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#n15&quot; name=&quot;n15&quot;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;                    &lt;span class=&quot;predefined&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span class=&quot;local-variable&quot;&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;).attr(&lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;delimiter&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;src&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;delimiter&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&quot;predefined&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;.iconise.data[icon]);
&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#n16&quot; name=&quot;n16&quot;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;                }
&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#n17&quot; name=&quot;n17&quot;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;            }
&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#n18&quot; name=&quot;n18&quot;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;        })
&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#n19&quot; name=&quot;n19&quot;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;    };
&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#n20&quot; name=&quot;n20&quot;&gt;20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#n21&quot; name=&quot;n21&quot;&gt;21&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;})(jQuery);
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then to use it you need to build a database of icons. You simply call the iconise function to associate a name to a data: uri&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;CodeRay&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#n1&quot; name=&quot;n1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;predefined&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;.iconise(&lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;delimiter&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;myIcon&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;delimiter&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;delimiter&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;data:image/png;base64,/*...base64 encoded image...*/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;delimiter&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;);
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, you can reference your icon like this&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;CodeRay&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#n1&quot; name=&quot;n1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;tag&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;img&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;attribute-name&quot;&gt;src&lt;/span&gt;=&lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;delimiter&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;iconise:myIcon&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;delimiter&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;tag&quot;&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a bit of a quick and dirty hack, and it will certainly not degrade gracefully. But it might come in handy.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://twrl.github.com/2012/06/javascript-alternatives/</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://twrl.github.com/2012/06/javascript-alternatives/"/>
    <title>Javascript Alternatives</title>
    <published>2012-06-11T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-06-11T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Tom Robbins</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Over the last four weeks I&amp;rsquo;ve been rather busy with exams, but now that&amp;rsquo;s over I&amp;rsquo;m thinking computer again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been looking at some of the alternatives to JavaScript. In many ways JavaScript is a lovely little language, it&amp;rsquo;s incredibly flexible. But, the same dynamic type system that makes it so flexible also makes certain things very difficult (like writing or consuming modular APIs), and the prototype-based object system obscures many of the benefits of object-oriented programming. For some purposes these are strengths, because JavaScript can glue so many different things together without casting and without wrestling with common OO patterns like adapter or facade. Modularisation and componentisation are difficult, because with such weak typing it&amp;rsquo;s very difficult to check that interfaces are compatible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many alternatives out there, the big ones of the moment being Opa, Google Dart, and CoffeeScript. VBScript is also out there if you know you&amp;rsquo;re dealing with purely Internet Explorer clients, but the less said about VBScript the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not particularly like CoffeeScript. It has some very neat design ideas, but I personally find it less readable than regular JavaScript. I&amp;rsquo;m a curly bracket language boy, I like my start and end delimiters and consider indenting to be a style and readability thing. So while I can&amp;rsquo;t actually find anything to complain about with CoffeeScript, it just doesn&amp;rsquo;t suit my coding style.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On to Dart. Syntactically, it&amp;rsquo;s like a hybrid of C# and JavaScript, with a pinch of PHP. Which is fine, I have no objection to any of that. However, there are several things about Dart which make me rather uncomfortable. For a start I don&amp;rsquo;t agree with Google&amp;rsquo;s design decisions about the Dart VM, although that&amp;rsquo;s minor. Dart is designed to operate in the client, with a Dart-to-JavaScript transpiler as a transition measure, but I don&amp;rsquo;t expect to see a Dart VM implemented in anything but Google Chrome any time soon. It&amp;rsquo;s also far from clear how Dart interoperates with JavaScript - especially when the JavaScript comes packaged in AMD or CommonJS modules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which brings me to Opa. It&amp;rsquo;s rather neat, I was impressed. There are so many clever things in Opa, not least of which is the way it hides the details of communication between client and server. However, I&amp;rsquo;m not so keen on the way the markup tends to become fragments embedded in the program rather than the other way around - ASP.Net and PHP have done that pattern to death - and Opa leaves me feeling like I&amp;rsquo;m not entirely in control of the code that I&amp;rsquo;m writing. The point of Opa is to hide tricky details, especially of middleware, but it&amp;rsquo;s actually too good at what it does for comfort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which brings me back to JavaScript, but then I&amp;rsquo;m still stuck with the clunkyness of JavaScript for certain applications. Still, while it might not always be elegant, it does work. So for the time being, I&amp;rsquo;ll stick with JavaScript.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://twrl.github.com/2012/05/social-networking/</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://twrl.github.com/2012/05/social-networking/"/>
    <title>Social Networking</title>
    <published>2012-05-18T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-05-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Tom Robbins</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I like Google+. There&amp;rsquo;s a very good reason for this: integration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use Google Reader, Google Search, Google Drive, Google Calendar, Google Mail, Google Play, Google Chrome and Blogger. I use these things because Google is becoming the Unix of the web - a large set of simple, single-purpose tools that play nicely together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it&amp;rsquo;s only natural that I also want to use Google+ too. It would be so very convenient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two problems. First off, I&amp;rsquo;ve become too used to clicking &amp;ldquo;Log on with Facebook&amp;rdquo;. For a lot of services that I use, I&amp;rsquo;ve never actually created an account. This is not an insurmountable problem, I&amp;rsquo;ll live with more passwords in my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second is more substantial: I have around 350 Facebook friends. I have six friends who use Google+.   The update streams, photos, and so on I can work around or live without - but realtime interaction? I communicate a lot through facebook messages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since Facebook exposes it&amp;rsquo;s chat services through XMPP and social graph as a RESTful JSON service, you would think something could be done about this. But no, Facebook isn&amp;rsquo;t willing to play this game because they don&amp;rsquo;t want to lose users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which brings me back to the idea of Data Portability. Why can&amp;rsquo;t I keep my own little corner of the social graph, and Facebook and Google just provide services on top of it? In spite of the technical difficulties this is not such a crazy idea - there are plenty of solutions for distributed data storage and aggregation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the necessary technology already exists in the Diaspora project. Diaspora is distributed, but it still requires servers. It isn&amp;rsquo;t peer-to-peer in the way that we more usually associate with file sharing. You don&amp;rsquo;t run a Diaspora application on your PC when you want to access it - you have to run a well-connected server all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are schemes which could overcome the always-connected architecture for distributing social graph data, but doing the same thing for realtime interaction is more difficult. Keeping track of my chat and realtime messaging activities when I have hundreds of friends is much easier when there is a single, co-ordinating hub. It becomes next to impossible when there is no server and I&amp;rsquo;m using multiple clients on multiple devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that&amp;rsquo;s the challenge - can you keep distributed, continuously updated realtime data without some form of server infrastructure?&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://twrl.github.com/2012/05/who-am-i-standing-up-to-again/</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://twrl.github.com/2012/05/who-am-i-standing-up-to-again/"/>
    <title>Who am I standing up to again?</title>
    <published>2012-05-16T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-05-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Tom Robbins</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;There was an article today on the Huffington Post by Max Wind-Cowie called &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.huffingtonpost.co.uk/max-windcowie/gay-marriage-who-will-stand-up-to-the-hetero-phobes_b_1514024.html?ref=uk-politics&quot;&gt;Who Will Stand Up to the Hetero-Phobes?&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; - and it&amp;rsquo;s really got me seething. So much that I feel I have to rebut it. Here goes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A little while ago I wrote a piece for ConservativeHome about how the attacks and smears of the pro gay marriage campaign had shaken my belief in the cause to its foundations. The impulse to cry &amp;lsquo;paedo&amp;rsquo; every time a Catholic spoke of their discomfort over same sex marriage, the howls of &amp;lsquo;bigot&amp;rsquo; accompanying even the most gentle warning about potential implications - these are the characteristics of a movement that no longer believes it can win an argument and has instead decided to rely on ad hominem and vitriol. It is intolerant and it is ugly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three things here - first of all if your belief in a cause is so shaken by the actions of said cause&amp;rsquo;s supporters, that&amp;rsquo;s deeply concerning. Your belief was presumably not terribly strong, or &lt;em&gt;tu quoque&lt;/em&gt; would not be an issue. I don&amp;rsquo;t have to like what Israel gets up to in the middle east to oppose anti-semitism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;rsquo;t actually seen cries of &amp;lsquo;paedo&amp;rsquo; every time a Catholic speaks of sex, same-sex marriage, or the Roman church&amp;rsquo;s dogma regarding the subject - perhaps I&amp;rsquo;m looking in the wrong places. I have seen the pedophile priest debacle used to put pay to Catholic figures attempting to take the moral high ground on sexual ethics, especially when making &amp;ldquo;won&amp;rsquo;t somebody please think of the children&amp;rdquo; style arguments. While I&amp;rsquo;ll grant this is a rather crude tactic, it&amp;rsquo;s not a wholly inappropriate response to Catholic bishops claiming to be in a position of inviolable moral authority, in contrast to the evil homosexual agenda to turn everyone&amp;rsquo;s children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then there is the term bigot. I&amp;rsquo;m surprised that this needs explaining, but a bigot is by definition a prejudiced and intolerant person. So when somebody provides an objection to same-sex marriage which is not born of prejudice and intolerance, but instead comes from a balanced and rational appreciation of the relevant facts, then I shall refrain from calling them a bigot. When somebody provides an objection which is born of ignorance, stupidity, or centuries of institutionalised hatred and scapegoating, then I shall call them a bigot with impunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Over the last week we have seen further examples of the extent to which the gay rights militia has abandoned any moral authority and now seeks, apparently unashamedly, not to win through debate but to rob others of their right to speak.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is clearly misleading. To start with, the validity of the argument for same-sex marriage is not challenged by what Wind-Cowie perceives as heterophobia. I don&amp;rsquo;t feel I have some great &amp;lsquo;moral authority&amp;rsquo; to abandon - the LGBT movement is fighting for it&amp;rsquo;s rights, not for some moral ideal - we&amp;rsquo;re more like Mandelas than Ghandis. Neither is what follows a detriment to others&amp;rsquo; right to free speec, or it wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be if it had been reported accurately:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;First came the Advertising Standards Authority&amp;rsquo;s demand that the blogger &amp;lsquo;Archbishop Cranmer&amp;rsquo; answer for the adverts he had run on behalf of the Coalition for Marriage campaign. These ads - which showed heterosexual couples celebrating their nuptials and implored viewers to sign the coalition&amp;rsquo;s petition - apparently caused &amp;lsquo;hurt and offence&amp;rsquo; to some gay people. The only way in which one could possibly be &amp;lsquo;hurt&amp;rsquo; by the ad would be if one were somehow offended by the image of straight couples doing what straight couples have done for thousands of years - marrying one another. This isn&amp;rsquo;t a reaction against &amp;lsquo;hate speech&amp;rsquo; folks, it&amp;rsquo;s outright hetero-phobia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These readers responded to their &amp;lsquo;hurt&amp;rsquo; not by engaging in debate or navigating away from the page but by submitting complaints to the ASA - who have followed up in aggressive style and have frightened the man behind the avatar into hiring in the lawyers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the ASA, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pinknews.co.uk/2012/05/16/asa-responds-to-claim-it-persecuted-religious-blog-in-investigating-anti-gay-marriage-ad/&quot;&gt;the relevant complaints refer to the advert itself&lt;/a&gt; and in particular the (potentially) misleading 70% statistic from the ComRes/Catholic Voices poll. It is the advert which is under investigation, not the blogger who was contacted as part of said investigation. This appears to be the witness/suspect distinction gone awry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Next came the extraordinary decision by the Law Society to withdraw permission for an event on the role of heterosexual marriage in a good and just society. Cristina Odone (who was due to speak at the event alongside my friend Phillip Blond) has written for the Telegraph that the decision was taken on the basis that a discussion of heterosexual marriage contravened the esteemed society&amp;rsquo;s &amp;lsquo;diversity policy&amp;rsquo;. Apparently diversity - for the Law Society at least - stretches only one way in the discussion of public policy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The event in question was a colloquium held by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcongress.org/&quot;&gt;World Congress of Families&lt;/a&gt;, a religiously motivated, US-led, conservative organisation whose stated principles include such gems as &amp;ldquo;Marriage between a man and a woman forms the sole moral context for natural sexual union. Whether through pornography, promiscuity, incest or homosexuality, deviations from these created sexual norms cannot truly satisfy the human spirit.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I sincerely doubt that what they had in mind was a balanced debate - apparently the Law Society agrees, although they have not to my knowledge publicly commented. Would it be appropriate for the Law Society to host a well-rounded debate on a contentious issue of public policy: eminently. Would it be appropriate for the Law Society to host a group of people, most if not all of whom are already in broad agreement, ranting at each other about how LGBT people are seeking to undermine society: absolutely not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rights of Christina Odone and others to free expression are not compromised by the Law Society refusing to be their soapbox. One person&amp;rsquo;s right to free speech does not give somebody else an obligation to be their platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;And this is the problem. I too believe in diversity. I&amp;rsquo;m a gay man (who, as it happens, believes that gay marriage is the right way forward for our society) who has benefited from our tradition of allowing a plurality of views and for the open discussion of what is good and right and what is bad and wrong. Were it not for Britain&amp;rsquo;s tolerance of dissent who would have been brave, or foolish, enough to argue that people like me ought not be imprisoned for our sexual desires?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this at least we are in agreement. However, I see the matter of diversity, equality and fairness rather differently - perhaps more pessimistically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a sad truth that in our society people can&amp;rsquo;t simply expect to be treated fairly, instead we must have and use the law to enforce &amp;lsquo;fairness&amp;rsquo;. As a society we have determined that who you love is a characteristic that leads to people being treated unfairly, and is worthy of being so protected. We have not determined that who you hate is a characteristic worthy of the same consideration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But people&amp;rsquo;s fundamental rights continue unabridged. Refusing to indulge anti-gay groups publicity stunts, or asking awkward questions of fundamentalist bloggers, is not comparable with the criminalisation of homosexuality. Sixty years ago both Wind-Cowie and myself would either have been imprisoned or chemically castrated - that Christina Odone had to air her views on the website of the Telegraph instead of the floor of the Law Society is minutiae by comparison. Last week, as happens alarmingly often the world over, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2012/05/11/jay-corey-jones-gay-minnesota-teen-suicide_n_1510001.html&quot;&gt;it was widely reported that a teenager committed suicide after a campaign of homophobic bullying&lt;/a&gt; - not an event which is analogous to a badly worded letter from the ASA bruising somebody&amp;rsquo;s feelings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Yet that very word, &amp;lsquo;diversity&amp;rsquo;, has now come to represent not plurality but homogeneity, not dissent but repression. Hiding behind it, secularists and the ayatollahs of social liberalism are able to strip public discourse of the bits they don&amp;rsquo;t like - faith, orthodoxy, skepticism about change. They have been able to use the frame of diversity as a weapon against its very purpose; to shut out and shut up those with whom they disagree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s time for those gay men and women who genuinely prize freedom to take a stand against those who act against it in our name. It is up to us to continue winning the argument for the freedoms our society permits us - not to preserve those freedoms at the expense of others&amp;rsquo; consciences or right to speak. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faith has no place in the machinery of state. If the law must reflect the Catholic religious view that I should not marry, why should it not reflect the hardline Islamic view that I deserve to be stoned to death? Or the pastafarian view that everybody eat spaghetti and meatballs once a week? Regardless of my personal views on religion, it has no place in the state - otherwise where do you draw the line. The price of religious freedom is freedom from religion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The argument for same-sex marriage is already won.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fight now is social - it&amp;rsquo;s holding teachers accountable for the fact that homophobia is not just &amp;lsquo;playground banter&amp;rsquo;, it pointing out the demeaning and devaluing implications of &amp;ldquo;love the sinner, hate the sin&amp;rdquo;, and so on. If that&amp;rsquo;s what people wish to believe or profess then so be it, but their right to believe these things and profess these things does not prevent me from arguing with them, nor from shaming them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If my society gives me the right to marry I want that right to have sprung from a collective judgment, not from the authoritarian zeal of those acting, supposedly, on my behalf. Let&amp;rsquo;s leave the hetero-phobia at the door and get on with the business of political and moral debate. For goodness sake gays, stop whinging about people who disagree with you - argue with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The collective judgement seems to agree with us right now, but anyone foolish enough to believe that the will of the majority can guarantee peoples rights has an alarmingly short memory. If collective judgement were the only force for change, maybe we would be imprisoned after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This whole style of thought, putting principle before practice; think tanks, rhetorical style and Westminster politics before suicide rates, homophobic crime and homelessness; this moral high ground, the concept that we must protect the freedom of the people who hate us; this is the biggest challenge which we now face in advancing the cause of LGBT equality - it&amp;rsquo;s within ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s our instinct: be normal, take the moral high ground, articulate your complaints, reason with the unreasonable, conform, integrate, assimilate, play the game. This is how we earn our place at the table: &amp;ldquo;He&amp;rsquo;s gay but he&amp;rsquo;s a nice chap,&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Isn&amp;rsquo;t she pretty, she used to be a man don&amp;rsquo;tchaknow.&amp;rdquo; That&amp;rsquo;s not a table I want to sit at - we can carve out other places in society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Equality before the law is but a stones throw away - an equal place in society is shaping up to be a much longer and more bitter fight, and greatest opponents may yet prove to be each other.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://twrl.github.com/2012/05/wheres-my-data/</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://twrl.github.com/2012/05/wheres-my-data/"/>
    <title>Where's my Data!</title>
    <published>2012-05-15T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-05-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Tom Robbins</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have Facebook. I have Google+, Google Docs, Google Play, GMail, Blogger, Picasa and various other Google products. I have a Live@edu email account. I have a github account, a SourceForge account, a cloud9 account, and a Hojoki account. I have an account with Ocado and another with Tesco, and one with Amazon. I have at least two OpenIDs, and a dozen more services which I routinely use by federated logon to one of the above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have accounts with online services that I don&amp;rsquo;t even remember exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My online identity is no longer a discrete thing. It&amp;rsquo;s a big ball of fuzz, at best. And because of the overload of accounts none of them use any sort of particularly strong credentials. I choose decent passwords, but that&amp;rsquo;s a good as it gets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is data. I&amp;rsquo;ve recently become acutely aware of how spread out my data is across so many different services. My contacts experience five-way synchronisation between Google, Live, Facebook, my Laptop and my Phone - and I have this sneaking suspicion that I&amp;rsquo;ve missed some. I don&amp;rsquo;t even know where my data is any more, I can&amp;rsquo;t use half of it when I want it because even if I do remember where it is, access is only ensured by the stored passwords and cookies in my web browser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have an architectural problem. I want my data! It&amp;rsquo;s mine! I want to use your services to work with my data - I don&amp;rsquo;t want to use your services to work with your copy of a subset of my data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and it would be nice if it were all transparent. If I could chop and change services, just like I can now but without the hassle of exporting and re-importing all my data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technologically speaking this is pretty easy. A triplestore in the cloud, augmented by some sort of bulk storage. OAuth to control access by different service providers, data synchronisation so that I can keep my data (or subsets of it) available offline. OpenID to federate your login to everything, and X.509 certificates, or even a hardware token, to authenticate to your identity provider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of this actually requires any new breakthrough - but &amp;lsquo;the cloud&amp;rsquo; is primarily an infrastructure for service providers, rather than one for users. The money is in selling multiply-redundant block storage by the trillions of bytes, or processor-hours by the hundred thousand a month. It&amp;rsquo;s not in providing semi-structured storage (with the overheads that entails) for a steady 300-500GB of my accumulated junk.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://twrl.github.com/2012/03/initialising-web-workers/</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://twrl.github.com/2012/03/initialising-web-workers/"/>
    <title>Initialising Web Workers</title>
    <published>2012-03-28T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-03-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Tom Robbins</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;apos;ve had tonsillitis over the last 5 days or so, so I&amp;apos;ve spent most of the last few days in a bit of a daze, idly tinkering with random things to pass the time. As with much idle tinkering, it&amp;apos;s all a bit rough and ready, but here is one snippet which might prove useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was tinkering with Web Workers and I wanted to be able to load up Require.js in a worker and then pass it the name of a main module. So I wrote this stub, lets call it w.js, which goes in the same directory as require.js (which will be Require&amp;rsquo;s baseDir - told you it was a bit rough). You can then create your worker by doing&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;CodeRay&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#n1&quot; name=&quot;n1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; worker = &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; Worker(&lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;delimiter&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;scripts/w.js?main=myapp/main&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;delimiter&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;);
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and Require.js will be loaded into your module, which will in turn load your main. As a fringe benefit you get a nice global object called query which contains all parameters passed in the query string.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;CodeRay&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#n1&quot; name=&quot;n1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; params = self.location.search.substring(&lt;span class=&quot;integer&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;).split(&lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;delimiter&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;delimiter&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;), query = {};
&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#n2&quot; name=&quot;n2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#n3&quot; name=&quot;n3&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; (&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; i &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; params) {
&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#n4&quot; name=&quot;n4&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; sp = params[i].split(&lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;delimiter&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;delimiter&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;),
&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#n5&quot; name=&quot;n5&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;        n = sp[&lt;span class=&quot;integer&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;],
&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#n6&quot; name=&quot;n6&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;        v = unescape(sp[&lt;span class=&quot;integer&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;]);
&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#n7&quot; name=&quot;n7&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;    query[n] = v;
&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#n8&quot; name=&quot;n8&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;}
&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#n9&quot; name=&quot;n9&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#n10&quot; name=&quot;n10&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;delete&lt;/span&gt; params;
&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#n11&quot; name=&quot;n11&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#n12&quot; name=&quot;n12&quot;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; require = { &lt;span class=&quot;key&quot;&gt;deps&lt;/span&gt; : [ query.main ] };
&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#n13&quot; name=&quot;n13&quot;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;span class=&quot;line-numbers&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#n14&quot; name=&quot;n14&quot;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;importScripts(&lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;delimiter&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;require.js&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;delimiter&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;);
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I know this is not terribly exciting - parsing a query string is pretty basic stuff in Javascript - but when I first tried this I was looking at a one-off message handler to initialise the global context in the worker. Because workers share so few API&amp;rsquo;s with an ordinary web page, it&amp;rsquo;s easy to forget the few that they have in common, and one of them is location.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some more advanced cases the message handler might still be the best way forward, but to get a few name-value pairs in this is a lovely little trick.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://twrl.github.com/2012/03/ajax-and-file-uris/</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://twrl.github.com/2012/03/ajax-and-file-uris/"/>
    <title>Ajax and file&#58;// URIs</title>
    <published>2012-03-28T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2012-03-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Tom Robbins</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ajax is becoming the dominant method, if it isn&amp;rsquo;t already, of getting data in and out of a web application. But Ajax is built on top of XMLHttpRequest, which as the name suggests is only really well defined if the underlying protocol is HTTP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what about local files? The new Filesystem API&amp;rsquo;s are coming, but they sandbox us heavily. At least for the time being, if we want to muck about with self-modifying code or local file-based data sources we have to hack it, which means using any one of half a dozen browser and/or os specific methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I quite like having a consistent API to work with, which you can&amp;rsquo;t easily have under these circumstances. Fortunately, the lovely folks at TiddlyWiki have provided &lt;a href=&quot;http://jquery.tiddlywiki.org/twFile.html&quot;&gt;a jQuery plugin&lt;/a&gt; which abstracts their general purpose file load and save functionality, so you have a load and a save function exposed and how those are best implemented is determined for you automatically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it&amp;rsquo;s still not a single consistent API for getting data in and out. Having load and save methods for the local filesystem is lovely if all I want to do is load and save from the local filesystem, but what if I want to use a resource which may or may not be local. I would like to treat a directory full of JSON files on the local system the same as a REST interface on a remote server, and the only thing I want to change is the base URI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;jQuery now supports the &lt;code&gt;$.ajaxTransport&lt;/code&gt; method, which allows us to define custom ways in which jQuery&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;$.ajax&lt;/code&gt; method is implemented for different circumstances. It&amp;rsquo;s relatively easy to use this to intercept Ajax queries to file:// URIs, and translate them into load and save calls based on whether they&amp;rsquo;re GET or PUT. I&amp;rsquo;ve hacked together a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/twrl/tinker/blob/master/js/jquery/localJax.js&quot;&gt;jQuery plugin&lt;/a&gt; to do just that, remapping Ajax queries on local files to the equivalent calls on TiddlyWiki&amp;rsquo;s twFile plugin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As cool as this is, it&amp;rsquo;s only half the story. We don&amp;rsquo;t just use Ajax to GET and PUT to RESTful data, we use it for all sorts of other things. It makes no sense to define a behaviour for a POST to local files in general. However, Web Workers potentially change that. An Ajax post to a local javascript could be interpreted as a command to load that javascript as a web worker, and then pass the query data into the worker as a message and wait for a response. Or it could not. The scenario is rather complicated, but certainly worth thinking about.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://twrl.github.com/2012/03/rehashing-xml/</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://twrl.github.com/2012/03/rehashing-xml/"/>
    <title>Rehashing Xml</title>
    <published>2012-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Tom Robbins</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I find it interesting sometimes to consider, if I were starting over and designing &lt;em&gt;xyz-thing&lt;/em&gt; from scratch, what would I do differently to what we already have. Recently I&amp;rsquo;ve been considering this with XML.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trouble with XML is that it&amp;rsquo;s a vast stack of standards. In some ways this is a good thing, because at least in theory it adds a lot of flexibility for different use cases. But it does result in duplication and redundancy, because document authors never know exactly which editions of which specs are being used by which processors and vice versa. How often do we see patterns like the common one for the language attribute on the HTML tag:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;html xmlns=&quot;http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot; xml:lang=&quot;en&quot;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The common &lt;code&gt;id&lt;/code&gt; attribute is the same. It sounds like a trivial niggle, but actually it&amp;rsquo;s a design flaw in how these applications (XHTML and XML in this case) are layered one on top of the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we have the DOM, the XML Infoset, EXI, Canonical XML, XML Namespaces, XML Schema and so on. It&amp;rsquo;s a dizzying array of specs, each with complex demands, which is partly why WHATWG have moved away from the idea of XHTML and put their efforts into HTML5&amp;rsquo;s SGML derived syntax instead. Complying with the existing stack of XML specifications is too onerous, and the specs themselves are not always neatly joined up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throw in stuff from the edges of the XML world - the development of IRIs, XRIs and CURIEs, the semantic models of RDF, the multipart MIME types and the data: URI scheme, and so on - and it&amp;rsquo;s a recipe for migraines and sleepless nights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all it&amp;rsquo;s flaws however, XML has a whole host of benefits too. There is a very good reason why it&amp;rsquo;s so widely adopted, it&amp;rsquo;s is very flexible and it is human readable, it is (relatively) easy to parse, validate and transform. There various stable and well understood means to map programmatic objects into XML serialisations and back, enabling everything from RPC to Active Record to be done using it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if I was going to redesign XML from scratch, what would I do? Well, here are my main thoughts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scrap DTDs, completely. I&amp;rsquo;m sure there&amp;rsquo;s been other occasions, but the last time that I can think of when I saw a DTD used seriously was when XHTML 1.1 was published, and XML Schema wasn&amp;rsquo;t considered &amp;lsquo;mature&amp;rsquo; at the point.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Design the Infoset first. Infoset is supposed to represent the logical model of a document, which XML serialises and DOM provides programmatic access to. Standard XML syntax need not be the only serialisation of an XML Infoset, and the DOM can be made to converge more closely with the underlying model.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Take a cue from Architecture of the World Wide Web, and consider information items in your infoset as akin to resources. That means that an element might be considered to have a set of zero or more Descriptions, Identifiers, and Representations. Identifiers can be XPath expressions, IDs or any other unique reference to an element. Descriptions are any old metadata, and Representations correspond to different serialisations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Design a processing model to go with the infoset. XML Schema defines the PSVI, XSLT defines the post transformation infoset, XML Encryption defines post encryption/decryption infosets. A general model for the transformation of one infoset into the next, and pipelining those transformations, would be very useful.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consider all element and attribute names as URIs. Instead of QName we can use URIorCURIE as the type of all namespace qualified names.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use processing instructions for instructions to the processor. That means rather than xmlns:foo=&amp;rdquo;&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; on an element we insert a processing instruction &lt;?namespace foo=&quot;...&quot;?&gt;. If qualified names are now URIs, then we are telling the processor how to expand any CURIEs that we are using. We might also have processing instructions for associating schemas, transforms, even linkbases. Processing instructions can be used to set up the document-specific processing pipeline described above, linking together various flavours of infoset transformation as well as controlling how the infoset is generated from the serialised document. Anything which alters the processing of the document when viewed as a series of parser events. Using attributes for this sort of thing should be limited strictly to when we are giving an element specific instruction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One day I might do a skunk works and draft something along these lines, until then I can but rant.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://twrl.github.com/2012/03/whatever-happened-to-osid/</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://twrl.github.com/2012/03/whatever-happened-to-osid/"/>
    <title>Whatever Happened To Osid</title>
    <published>2012-03-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-03-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Tom Robbins</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Five years ago, or so, we had a wonderful suite of open, abstract API&amp;rsquo;s developed by a group led out of MIT and calling themselves the Open Knowledge Initiative. These API&amp;rsquo;s were the Open Service Interface Definitions, and although they had a definite flavour of Java about them, the specs were deliberately designed to be platform neutral.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OKI now appears to be defunct, but a lot of what they produced is still &lt;a href=&quot;http://sourceforge.net/projects/okiproject&quot;&gt;sitting there on SourceForge&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now a lot of this was useless nonsense, at least, outside of certain specialist applications. I know there are people that do, but I personally have no wish to keep track of who is enrolled on which course. Application specific is not general purpose. However, there are some very good general purpose abstractions in there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Filing, for example, provides a highly abstracted representation of any filing system (which is anything which consists of trees of containers and byte-streams). Hierarchy is not dissimilar, abstracting anything which is hierarchical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;and-your-point-is&quot;&gt;And your point is&amp;hellip;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Javascript. My point is Javascript.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until relatively recently, Javascript was a domain specific language. It was used for scripting, in particular in the context of web browsers. Suddenly, Javascript is seeing general purpose use - largely due to the introduction of Node and Rhino. Equally, we&amp;rsquo;re seeing the boundary between web and desktop applications blurring, courtesy of HTML5 amongst others. The use cases for Javascript have exploded, they&amp;rsquo;re vast, they&amp;rsquo;re everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the only fully standardised API we have is DOM, and nobody fully complies with that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a soft spot for OSID, because it was in vogue a the time when I was teaching myself concepts like middleware and n-tier architecture. However, clean, pure and platform neutral abstractions like those which make up a large part of the OSID specs are a perfect starting point if we&amp;rsquo;re going to build up standard APIs for Javascript. CommonJS is achieving great things, but CommonJS is more concerned with the concept of a module than the content of a module.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hint of Java in OSID only adds to the attraction, because Javascript is so frequently sandboxed. A Java-like API has an advantage getting around this, because most sandboxing environments support some kind of Java liveconnect or equivalent, allowing us to use Java to implement any privileged elements (with associated benefits of code signing and code security policies being built into the JVM). As TiddlyWiki was forced to do, we can implement things like low-level filesystem access as a Java applet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;but&quot;&gt;But&amp;hellip;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Javascript&amp;rsquo;s type system is prototype-based, not class-based. This means that there is no native concept of an interface, nor can types be attributed in a standard way like they can in environments such as CLI. So defining a load of interfaces and implementations of those interfaces is not something which makes sense in the context of Javascript.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alas, there is no standard API in Javascript for emulating these things either. Various projects like Joose provide a metaobject framework, but there isn&amp;rsquo;t a common (or even a bunch of broadly similar) API for it in Javascript. So our interfaces are effectively just exercises in duck-typing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that&amp;rsquo;s where we start. In the first instance, our interfaces aren&amp;rsquo;t interfaces at all but a set of functions which test that an object conforms to the specification we&amp;rsquo;ve given.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve begun sketching this out as &lt;a href=&quot;http://github.com/twrl/osid.js&quot;&gt;a set of AMD modules on Github&lt;/a&gt;, but for the time being it&amp;rsquo;s all very basic.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://twrl.github.com/2012/03/im-fed-up-with-same--sex-marriage/</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://twrl.github.com/2012/03/im-fed-up-with-same--sex-marriage/"/>
    <title>I'm Fed Up With Same-sex Marriage</title>
    <published>2012-03-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-03-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Tom Robbins</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been a week and a half since the government launched the Equal Marriage Consultation, which means it&amp;rsquo;s been about twelve hours less than that since I responded and about a decade longer than that since it became a pressing social question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m bored with it already. The consultation period goes on until some time in mid June. Why do we need a twelve week consultation for something which the government has (a) already asked every official body which has an opinion about, and (b) the government has already decided to do and told everybody as much repeatedly?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suspect it&amp;rsquo;s a diversionary tactic. It keeps people like the bishops from looking too closely at the budget, and even if they do any unfortunate revelations about how it will have adverse effects on charities or people on lower incomes won&amp;rsquo;t be reported because some &lt;del&gt;old fool&lt;/del&gt; bishop or &lt;del&gt;drooling troglodyte&lt;/del&gt; tabloid journalist is far to busy getting over excited about &amp;ldquo;the gays want to marry, next thing they&amp;rsquo;ll want us to decriminalise sex!&amp;rdquo; or some such nonsense. It&amp;rsquo;s like fox hunting all over again - Tony Blair managed to drag that out for years, and whenever it looked like a political crisis was looming there&amp;rsquo;d be another debate on the Hunting Act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in the spirit of the debate, here are the key points for me: in our culture, marriage is considered to be a recognition of a long term romantic relationship, and it has specific cultural connotations about fidelity, interdependence and so on. Religious, as opposed to civil, marriage has further religious connotations. Civil partnerships, being a relatively new innovation, have much the same practical legal effect but much less of the cultural baggage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now since we&amp;rsquo;re recognising that there are a wide range of possible relationship styles and structures, none of which are intrinsically more or less valid than any other, it follows that there needs to be different styles of recognition to match. In addition to the legalisation of same-sex civil marriage, it&amp;rsquo;s therefore necessary to legalise mixed-sex civil partnerships and same-sex religious marriage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as religious marriage goes, I think it&amp;rsquo;s important not to confuse legalising something with mandating it - a distinction which many religious leaders, along with totalitarian dictators, seem not to grasp. Requiring religious groups to do something would have unpleasant religious freedom implications, but equally prohibiting them from doing something has many of the same problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, by giving all couples all three options, we give them the freedom to have their relationship recognised in the most appropriate way to them. Unrealistic expectations are a killer for relationships, even expectations of third parties, and branding a relationship as a &amp;ldquo;marriage&amp;rdquo; when those involved are much more comfortable with the label and connotation of a civil partnership is not going to help matters.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://twrl.github.com/2012/03/open-letter-to-britains-catholics/</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://twrl.github.com/2012/03/open-letter-to-britains-catholics/"/>
    <title>Open Letter - to Britain's Catholics on Same-sex Marriage</title>
    <published>2012-03-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-03-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Tom Robbins</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This open letter is to Roman Catholics in the UK. It is my response to the 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/religion/9124963/We-must-protect-true-meaning-of-marriage-says-Roman-Catholic-leader.html&quot;&gt;words of the Archbishop of Westminister&lt;/a&gt; 
which is due to be read in mass this coming Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I know your leaders are speaking to you, not for you, about same-sex marriage. 
I like to think that they&amp;rsquo;re trying to do their best, in good conscience, to 
stand by their beliefs and to steer you to stand by yours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Catholic Church is one of the most vocal groups in opposition to same-sex 
marriage. Like many of the opposing arguments, the water is being muddied with 
talk of polygamy and incest, of the degeneration of society into immorality, 
of HIV and adoption policy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;All of which somewhat misses the point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We live in the twenty-first century, not the twelfth: our ideal for marriage 
is not procreation or property rights, it&amp;rsquo;s love and commitment. Those other 
things might be important to us, or they might not, but they aren&amp;rsquo;t why two 
people choose to marry. The government&amp;rsquo;s spokesman put it exceptionally well 
when they said &amp;ldquo;if a couple love each other and want to commit to a life 
together&amp;hellip;they should have the option of a civil marriage irrespective of 
their sexual orientation.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the world in which we live, love is something which can seem to be sadly 
lacking. This surely is all the more reason to celebrate it, to recognise it. 
However fine their intentions, the recent outbursts from Cardinal O&amp;rsquo;Brien and 
others have been ironically hateful responses to people seeking that far more 
positive goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;So the question is, do you believe that two men, or two women, can love each 
other? I&amp;rsquo;m not sure what I can say that might persuade you of that. Hopefully 
it&amp;rsquo;s something that you know to be true already.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This weekend you will be told of your religious duty to oppose same-sex 
marriage. You will be told that extending marriage to same-sex couples will 
reduce it to nothing more than a &amp;ldquo;vague commitment between two people.&amp;rdquo; But if 
love and commitment are the defining features of marriage, then this has long 
been the case and extending it to same-sex couples will not change that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, the one and only thing that LGBT people are asking for 
is for their relationships to be acknowledged and celebrated in the same way 
as everybody else&amp;rsquo;s. Churches will not be asked to act against their 
conscience, the question is a secular one. There are no secular opposing 
arguments, not because they haven&amp;rsquo;t been made but because they haven&amp;rsquo;t 
withstood any scrutiny.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;After all, what harm can love do?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
 
</feed>